Alfred H. Barr, Jr. Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series 9a: Chronicles, ca. 1929-1970
  - The Museum of Modern Art: The First Ten Years, 1943; By A. C. Goodyear "The Museum Collection" pp. 83-90 (Box 1, Folder 9a.20)
  - The Museum of Modern Art: The First Ten Years by A. C. Goodyear, 1943. Loan Exhibitions: Ten Year Schedule (Box 1, Folder 9a.20A)
  - The Latin American Collection of The Museum of Modern Art, 1943; pp. 3-4 (Box 1, Folder 9a.21)
  - Museum of Modern Art Exhibits New Acquisitions Press Release, 7/22/1943 (Box 1, Folder 9a.22)
  - Minutes of the Meeting of the Advisory Committee of The Museum of Modern Art. Report of the Committee on the Museum Collections by James Johnson Sweeney, 12/8/1943 (Box 1, Folder 9a.23)
  - Structural Outline of the Museum Staff and Arrangement of the Collection, 1929-1943 (Box 1, Folder 9a.23A)
  - Bulletin of The Museum of Modern Art, Vol. XI, No.4, Feb.-March 1944. "New Acquisitions in American Painting" by J. T. Soby (Box 1, Folder 9a.24)
  - The Museum News, Vol. XXII, June 15, 1944, No.4. Acquisitions Policy of The Museum of Modern Art Painting and Sculpture by James Thrall Soby (Box 1, Folder 9a.25)
  - Art in America, October 1944. The Collection of The Museum of Modern Art: Four Basic Policies by James Thrall Soby (Box 1, Folder 9a.26)
  - The Museum Collections: A Brief Report, 1/15/1944; Letter to Philip Goodwin October 1944 concerning space division Minutes of Meeting of Executive Committee of the Board of Trustees of the Museum, April 27, 1944 concerning creation of a Chair of Modern Painting and Sculpture (Box 1, Folder 9a.27)
  - Report on the Private Exhibition of Paintings from the Collection of The Museum of Modern Art, arranged for the Trustees, 1/20/1945 (Box 1, Folder 9a.28)
  - Other Material in Connection With Folder 28 (Box 1, Folder 9a.28A)
  - Museum Committees Concerned with the Collection of Painting and Sculpture, 1929-1948 (Box 1, Folder 9a.29)
  - Policy for the collection of Painting and Sculpture, 1/24/1945; Also Fall 1944 A suggestion to the Trustees by J. T. Soby, J. J. Sweeney, and A.H.Barr, Jr. See also 28A (Box 1, Folder 9a.30)
  - Report to the Trustees in connection with a review of the Museum Collection, 1/1945 (Box 1, Folder 9a.30A)
  - The Museum of Modern Art in Transatlantic, June 1946, by J. T. Soby (Box 1, Folder 9a.31)
  - Reports and Brochures for Fund Raising, 1946, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9a.32)
  - Painting and Sculpture Collection Purchase Funds, 1940-1946; Miscellaneous material (Box 1, Folder 9a.33)
  - Agreement between the Metropolitan Museum of Art, The Museum of Modern Art, and the Whitney Museum of American Art, 9/15/1947 (Box 1, Folder 9a.34)
  - Agreement between the Metropolitan Museum of Art, The Museum of Modern Art, and the Whitney Museum of American Art, ca. 1947; First draft, extra copies (Box 1, Folder 9a.34A)
  - Agreement between the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Whitney Museum of American Art, and The Museum of Modern Art, 1947; Also: Termination of Agreement between Metropolitan Museum of Art and Whitney Museum, October 1, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9a.35)
  - The Metropolitan Museum and American Art, 1949-50 (Box 1, Folder 9a.36)
  - Policy on Museum Collections and Termination of Agreement with the Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9a.37)
  - Policy on Museum Collections and Termination of Metropolitan Agreement, ca. 1952-1953; From Trustees Meeting, December 11, 1952 ,and January 15, 1953 Statement of change of Policy, February 15, 1953 Policy Committee for the Museum's Collection of Masterworks, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9a.37A)
  - Second copy of 10.37A, ca. 1952-1953; Annotated by AHB (Box 1, Folder 9a.37B)
  - Policy Committee for the Museum's Collection of Masterworks - Minutes of Meetings, 1953-1957; 8 Meetings (Box 1, Folder 9a.38)
  - Painting and Sculpture Collection, 1947-1952; Miscellaneous letters, reports, etc. (Box 1, Folder 9a.39)
  - Painting and Sculpture Collection, 1953-1958; Miscellaneous memos, releases, etc. (Box 1, Folder 9a.40)
  - Priority lists of Paintings and Sculptures drawn up by AHB, 8/1961; Revised (Box 1, Folder 9a.41)
  - Painting and Sculpture Collection, 1959-1963; Miscellaneous Annual Reports, floor plans, etc. (Box 1, Folder 9a.42)
  - Museum Collections Floor Plan, 2nd and 3rd floors, 1964; Brochure for the Public (Box 1, Folder 9a.43)
  - Painting and Sculpture Collection, 1969; Miscellaneous articles (Box 1, Folder 9a.44)
  - Collection Policy: excerpts from the Chronicle, 1970; For William S. Paley (Box 1, Folder 9a.45)
  - Confidential Report to the Trustee ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of The Museum of Modern Art, 10/27/1965; Copy 4 Included: The Museum Collections - Outline of an Appendix and other related material (Box 1, Folder 9a.46)
  - Artists represented in other Departments of the Museum, In addition to those represented in the Painting and Sculpture Collection - for PASITMoMA listings (Box 1, Folder 9a.47)
  - PASITMoMA, Misc. memos Important (Box 1, Folder 9a.48)
  - Museum of Modern Art Publications on Painting and Sculpture Collection, 1942-1964; Prefaces, Forewords, etc. (Box 1, Folder 9a.49)
  - Painting and Sculpture in The Museum of Modern Art, 1977; Outline of Illustrations, Headings, etc. (Box 1, Folder 9a.50)
  - Painting and Sculpture in The Museum of Modern Art, Memos re production of the catalog (Box 1, Folder 9a.51)
  - Typed draft of PASITMoMA Chronicle in Blue binder, Chapts I - VI First version (Box 1, Folder 9a.52)
  - Typed draft of PASITMoMA Chronicle in 4 Blue binders, With relevant material re: quotes, statistics, etc. interleaved 2nd version Binder I: Chapters I and II Binder II: Chapter III Binder III: Chapters IV and V Binder IV: Chapters VI and VII (Box 1, Folder 9a.53)
- Series 10: Personal/Desk, 1927]-1973
  This Series includes items removed from AHB's desk drawers at 29 West 53rd Street; original order which was alphabetical in Subseries A, has been strictly maintained; quotation marks identifying file units reflect terminology used by Barr. Clive Phillpot has confirmed that "Mrs. Barr checked these papers 3/78 and 5/78."
  - Subseries A: Subject Areas, 1927]-1973
    - "American", 4 photos 2 articles 17" ca. 6 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.1 mf 3263:404)
    - "Arp Shapes" [Arp forms], 1940s; ca. 27 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.2 mf 3263:424)
    - "Bauhaus (Bayer, etc.)", 1940; 9 photos (Box 1, Folder 10.A.3 mf 3263:451)
    - "Baumeister - Chadwick", 1946; 20 plus items Folder labeled in WSL's hand (Box 1, Folder 10.A.4 mf 3263:462)
    - "Baynes" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.5 mf 3263:522)
    - "Belgium" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.6 mf 3263:538)
    - "Belgium" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.7 mf 3263:541)
    - "Biog.", Incl. 1920 CAA Program 1926 typedscript letter to ed. of Art News (Box 1, Folder 10.A.8 mf 3263:546)
    - "Biog.": MoMA AHB Tribute / evening, 1972, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.8.a mf 3263:556)
    - "Biog.": 60th Birthday celebration, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.8.b mf 3263:562)
    - "Biog.": "Biographical data; photos", 20 plus items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.8.c mf 3263:638)
    - "Biog.": "Barr - Ph.D. material", Incl. 1 item, 1940 letter PJS to AHB Rest of material sent to Deknatel May 1946l" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.8.d mf 3263:782)
    - "Bonnard" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.9 mf 3263:784)
    - "Boston 1948 Manifesto" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.10 mf 3263:801)
    - "Bracelli" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.11 mf 3263:834)
    - "British" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.12 mf 3263:843)
    - "C" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.13 mf 3263:879)
    - "Censorship", Incls. 1947 exchange btwn. AAR & MoMA staff (Box 1, Folder 10.A.14 mf 3263:888)
    - "Children's Art", Incl. letter w. ref. to C & AA Chart (Box 1, Folder 10.A.15 mf 3263:899)
    - "Chagall" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.16 mf 3263:914)
    - "Dali", Incl. 1 n.d. letter to M/M AHB Mostly photos, announcements (Box 1, Folder 10.A.17 mf 3263:916)
    - "Delmas", 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.18 mf 3263:973)
    - "Designs, etc.", 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.19 mf 3263:978)
    - "Dream and Dream Art" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.20 mf 3263:1023)
    - "Dreier", 1927; 2 letters Dreier to AHB See also, Series 1: Barr Correspondence, 1.1 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.21 mf 3263:1028)
    - "E", 1954; Letter E.A.T. Mesens to AHB re: Ernst (Box 1, Folder 10.A.22 mf 3263:1032)
    - "France - since 1940", Subtitled "Hilter and Art" by AHB Incl. AHB brief notes on Picasso & Matisse's activities (Box 1, Folder 10.A.23 mf 3263:1039)
    - "G", Incl. AHB notes on Kahnweiler/Gris lecture Gottlieb gall. announc'ts (Box 1, Folder 10.A.24 mf 3263:1051)
    - "German expressionist" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.25 mf 3263:1070)
    - "German artists 1933-45", See also, Series 9: Barr Writings 2 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.26 mf 3263:1076)
    - "German - Nazi", 12 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.27 mf 3263:1080)
    - "German - Neue Sachlichkeit" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.28 mf 3263:1100)
    - "Goodyear, A. Conger/Jeude Paume Exh.", 1932-1934, 1936-1938; Incl. corresp. Note from MSB: "correspondence handed over by A. Conger Goodyear about exhs. of Amer. Art in Paris, preceding & including the exh. at Jeude Paune 1938." (Box 1, Folder 10.A.29 mf 3263:1107)
    - "H", Letter, Hopper to AHB, 2/5/48 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.30 mf 3263:1256)
    - "Harnett - Peto", See also, Series 1: Barr Correspondence, folder 1.162 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.31 mf 3263:1258)
    - "Ren d'Harnoncourt", 1949, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.32 mf 3263:1274)
    - "Humanism" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.33 mf 3263:1289)
    - "Barr 'Ism' Dictionary", Incl. 55 sheets, yellowed, brittle paper 4 sheets of charts (Box 1, Folder 10.A.34 mf 3263:1300)
    - "Italian trip", 2 clippings (Box 1, Folder 10.A.35 mf 3263:1367)
    - "K", All illus. material 4 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.36 mf 3263:1373-1388)
    - "Kirstein, Lincoln": "Kerstein" [sic]", 1945; 7 items Letters/info. re: art in the Third Reich (Box 1, Folder 10.A.37.a mf 3264:20)
    - "Kirstein, Lincoln": "Kirstein reports on art and museum situation at the end of W.W. II", 1945; 30 items All addressed to Monroe Wheeler (MSB's hand) (Box 1, Folder 10.A.37.b mf 3264:60)
    - "L", Incl. 2 letters Jean Lurcat to AHB Typed notes Lecture by Leger (Box 1, Folder 10.A.38 mf 3264:130)
    - "Latin Amer. Speech", 17 sheets 8 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.39 mf 3264:149)
    - "Chicago, Ren. Society", 11 items Out of alphabetical sequence Kept here by AHB See also folder, 5.B.ll.a (filmed), where this speech is identified as "Art in our World" Incl. 1946 corresp Speech given April 17, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.40 mf 3264:172)
    - "Lieberman", 19 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.41 mf 3264:186)
    - "Life Symposium", 6/11-6/13/1949; Incl. mimeographed proceedings Life article Letters to ed. (Box 1, Folder 10.A.42 mf 3264:201)
    - "London" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.43 mf 3264:286)
    - "Louchheim", 1953-1956; Incl.NY Times articles (Box 1, Folder 10.A.44 mf 3264:304)
    - "M", Artists (Box 1, Folder 10.A.45 mf 3264:339)
    - "Matta photos etc. important", Incl. 3 n.d. sheets of AHB notes (1 191j) w. diagram 0.25": 5 items Some 20 plus sheets each (Box 1, Folder 10.A.46 mf 3264:359)
    - "Mexican Report", 1942; 5 items Incl. 4 sheet typescript (Box 1, Folder 10.A.47 mf 3264:366)
    - "Miscellaneous Clippings", 1949, 1950, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.48 mf 3264:374)
    - "Miscellaneous photos", 5 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.49 mf 3264:439)
    - "Miller, Dorothy C.", ca. 1952-1959; re: Smith Honorary Degree (Box 1, Folder 10.A.50 mf 3264:449)
    - "N", 4 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.51 mf 3264:556)
    - "Nadelman", 1 item Incl. 10 sheet typed chronology Author not known (Box 1, Folder 10.A.52 mf 3264:566)
    - "Nationalism", 1945, 1946, 1948; Clippings (Box 1, Folder 10.A.53 mf 3264:578)
    - "P", 3 items Incl. catalog of 1st Pollock exh. at Art of this Century 1940 article AHB marked "postaste" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.54 mf 3264:582)
    - "Paris School - miscel." (Box 1, Folder 10.A.55 mf 3264:678)
    - "Pan American Union", 5 photos 1945 corresp. for Leslie Switzer (Box 1, Folder 10.A.56 mf 3264:690)
    - "Penguin - artists", 1945; See also folders 6.A.2.a-f: incls. 4" of material relevant to this subject (Box 1, Folder 10.A.57.a mf 3264:725)
    - "Penguin - Blume", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.57.b mf 3264:727)
    - "Penguin - Authors, text", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.57.c mf 3264:755)
    - "Penguin authors", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.57.d mf 3264:757)
    - "Penguin - Lists", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.57.e mf 3264:758)
    - "Penguin - miscellaneous", 1945; 16 items Incl. letter S.C. Clark/AHB re: royalty fees (Box 1, Folder 10.A.57.f mf 3264:788)
    - "Post Impressionists", 4 items Incl. Meyer Schapiro letter 7/25/35 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.58 mf 3264:810)
    - "Pro-Modern", 1941, 1953; 6 items See also, Series 7: Political Controversy folder 7.21a and 7.21b (Box 1, Folder 10.A.59 mf 3264:819)
    - "Psychological", Incl. printed matter, 1957 1950, 1946, 1945, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.60 mf 3264:851)
    - "R", 6 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.61 mf 3264:881)
    - "Religious Art, Modern", ca. 1944-1953; 14 items See also Series 4 and Series 6, folder 6.B.12. Incl. 9 sheets of AHB writing (Box 1, Folder 10.A.62 mf 3264:891)
    - "Richmond", 1949, 1950-1952; AHB v. Ross Valentine & the Richmond Times Dispatch (Box 1, Folder 10.A.63 mf 3264:953)
    - "Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich" - From desk drawer, 1948, 1947, 1939, 1936, 1935, 1934; Incl. AHB - AAR 11/6/33 re: Bliss Coll. ca. 26 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.64.a mf 3264:998)
    - "Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich" - From envelope marked "confidential", ca. 1934-1944; See MSB note: ca. 1.5", corresp. to/from A.C. Goodyear, AAR, AHB See also, Series 1: AHB Corresp. folders 1.2, 1.59, 1.191 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.64.b.i mf 3264:1108)
    - "Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich" - From envelope marked "confidential", ca. 1929-1933 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.64.b.ii mf 3264:1157)
    - "Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich" - "Gifts of Art" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.64.c.i mf 3264:1283)
    - "Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich" - "Gifts of Art" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.64c.ii mf 3264:1348-1371 mf 3265:19)
    - "Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich" - "Gifts of Art" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.64.c.iii mf 3265:191)
    - "Romanticism 19th" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.65 mf 3265:256)
    - "Rouault", Letter Gordon Washburn/AHB (Box 1, Folder 10.A.66 mf 3265:270)
    - "S", Illus./printed matter 8 photos (Box 1, Folder 10.A.67 mf 3265:281)
    - "Siqueiros", 3 items 2 photos & booklet (Box 1, Folder 10.A.68 mf 3265:297)
    - "Soby", 8 items Incl. 5 Sat Rev. pieces 1947, 46 2 1957 letters; See also, Series 1: Barr Correspondence and Series 6: Exhibitions/Publications (Box 1, Folder 10.A.69 mf 3265:323)
    - "The State and Art", 16 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.70 mf 3265:364)
    - "Surrealism, Dada etc.", 35 items Printed matter (some annotated) Photos 1932 Wads-Athem brochure 1940s, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 10.A.71 mf 3265:417)
    - "Insane", 4 items This folder, not in alphabetical sequence, might have been kept here because it was related to "Surrealism, Dada, etc." AHB included the art of the insane in his 1936 FADS exhibition Much of the material in the preceding folder dates from 1936 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.72 mf 3265:478)
    - "Sweeney", 1946; 7 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.73 mf 3265:486)
    - "Swiss Booklets", 1946; 5 items Re: AmerVach Verlag of Basel, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10.A.74 mf 3265:498)
    - "T", 2 items "artists that begin with a 'T'" (Box 1, Folder 10.A.75 mf 3265:506)
    - "Unanswered", 1946; Mimeographed 1 item (Box 1, Folder 10.A.76 mf 3265:518)
    - "U.S.A.", 1945, 1946, 1948; 6 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.77 mf 3265:526)
    - "War and Art", 1 item (Box 1, Folder 10.A.78 mf 3265:565)
    - "Z", 2 items (Box 1, Folder 10.A.79 mf 3265:569)
  - Subseries B: Bryn Mawr: Mary Flexner Lectures: "Dogma and Practice in Modern Art", 1942, 1945-1946
    See also, Series 5: Barr Lectures, Talks/Speeches 5.B.11.a and 5.B.11.b
    - "Miscellaneous", Typescript of part of lecture AHB notes and cards (Box 1, Folder 10.B.1 mf 3265:579)
    - "General", The College News Announcement/outline of lecture series Post lecture corresp., May/Apr. 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10.B.2 mf 3265:600)
    - "Correspondence", 2/1945-3/1946 (Box 1, Folder 10.B.3 mf 3265:633)
    - "Exhibition", Incl. AHB diagrams, lists (Box 1, Folder 10.B.4 mf 3265:702)
    - "Bryn Mawr", Incl. quotations AHB seems to have set aside for use in lectures (Box 1, Folder 10.B.5 mf 3265:718)
    - "I Modern ... (machine)", 11 Feb. 1946; For lecture "Art should be modern - the rise and decline of the machine" (Box 1, Folder 10.B.6 mf 3265:746)
    - "II", 2/18/1946; Re: lecture "Art should be pure - with a glance at utilitarian consequences" (Box 1, Folder 10.B.7 mf 3265:809)
    - "III (Fantastic)", 2/25/1946; Re: lecture "Art should be marvelous - visual poetry of enigma and fantasy" (Box 1, Folder 10.B.8 mf 3265:875)
    - "IV Intense", 3/4/1946; Re: lecture "Art should be - anxiety, violence, ectasy" Incl. cards, typed notes, lists, etc. (Box 1, Folder 10.B.9a mf 3265:942)
    - "B.M.(Intense)", 1949, 1950; Incl. clippings and printed matter (Box 1, Folder 10.B.9b mf 3265:1000)
    - "National V", 3/11/1946; Re: lecture "Art should be National - varieties of racial and regional self-esteem" (Box 1, Folder 10.B.10 mf 3265:1066)
    - "VI Social", 3/18/1946; Re: lecture "Art should be social - the state of the world; propaganda and prophecy" (Box 1, Folder 10.B.11 mf 3265:1081)
  - Subseries C: MoMA Related, 1932-1969
    - "Safety", 1961-1962; Removed: Category #3 (Box 1, Folder 10.C.1 mf 3265:1100)
    - "Classification of Collections for purposes of protection in case of war", Removed: Category #3 (Box 1, Folder 10.C.2 mf 3265:1100)
    - "1969: Lowry Resignation": Paley - Barr (Box 1, Folder 10.C.3 mf 3265:1102)
    - "1953: Bill of Rights Conference"; "Emergency Civil Liberties Com." (Box 1, Folder 10.C.4 mf 3265:1110)
    - "1947: Museum Collection - Drawing Exhibition" (Box 1, Folder 10.C.5 mf 3265:1146)
    - "Acquisitions", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10.C.6 mf 3265:1195)
    - "Col. Instal.", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10.C.7 mf 3265:1205)
    - "Col. Lists", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10.C.8 mf 3265:1227)
    - "Collection - Trustee opinions", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10.C.9 mf 3265:1256)
    - "Time Analysis", 1936, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10.C.10 mf 3265:1265)
    - "Answered", 1944; 2 letters from Leslie Switzer (Box 1, Folder 10.C.11 mf 3265:1277)
    - "Garden 1942" (Box 1, Folder 10.C.12 mf 3265:1289)
    - "Perm Col Instal", n.d., 1941 (Box 1, Folder 10.C.13 mf 3265:1297)
    - "Constitution (as amended Dec. 12, 1939)" (Box 1, Folder 10.C.14 mf 3265:1306)
    - "Selected Items":The Museum Collections a brief report, 1/15/1944; 1st draft (Box 1, Folder 10.C.15.a mf 3265:1316)
    - "Selected Items": AHB to SCC, 11/1941 (Box 1, Folder 10.C.15.b mf 3265:1316)
    - "Selected Items": Philip Goodwin to PJ, 1/10/1941 (Box 1, Folder 10.C.15.c mf 3265:1316)
    - "Selected Items", 1939; re: reopening of MoMA, 1939: NAR - AHB 7/27/39 A.C.Goodyear - AHB 5/22/39 AHB - PJS 5/5/39 (Box 1, Folder 10.C.15.d mf 3265:1316)
    - "1937 Current Activities and the Future Program of The Museum of Modern Art Congressional Questionnarie", 50 pages (Box 1, Folder 10.C.16 mf 3265:1333-1392)
    - "1933": "10/33 'The Permanent Collection'", 5 sheets, typed AHB report, October 1933, Loan exhibition, 10 sheets (Box 1, Folder 10.C.17.a mf 3266:19)
    - "1933": Master copy Loan Exhibition: Ten Year Schedule (complete) ... by AHB, Jr.", 5/1933; 23 typed pages (Box 1, Folder 10.C.17.b mf 3266:81)
    - "Suggested exhibitions 1933/Schemes for MoMA 1933 (Blackburn)", 1932-1933; "Exhbition/Lists of suggestions" by AHB, Ascona, May 27, 1933: "This list was begun in December, 1932, outlined in March and completed on the above date: it may prove out of date in some particulars. Dec. '33 /s/ AHB" 24 typed sheets Fragile (Box 1, Folder 10.C.18 mf 3266:120)
  - Subseries D: Art Workers' Coalition
    - Art Workers' Coalition, 1969; Miscellaneous printed matter Printed matter Proclamation 15 items 3 misc items: printed matter (Box 1, Folder 10.D.1 mf 3266:163 mf 3266:180-182)
- Series 11: Matisse, 1946, 1949-1975
  The Series consists of documentation produced in 1946 and from 1949 through ca. 1975 by Alfred H. Barr, Jr., on the artist Henri Matisse (1869-54) and located in The Museum of Modern Art Archives. Included are a variety of record types: letters, notes, memoranda, phono recordings, photographs, reproductions, two 3-x-5" index-card files and a reel tape recording. Items have been arranged in the organic units in which they were logically accumulated. Thus, three Subgroups have been established on the basis of their functional origins: Matisse Book, Matisse Exhibition and Matisse post-publication material. In some instances several record types can be found in one Series; for example, phono records and written notes are included in Matisse I.B. Subgroup IV was established on the basis of record types. Subgroup V consists of materials collected by AHB but given to the Museum later by Margaret Scolari Barr.
  Selected noteworthy correspondents include Clive Bell, Bernard Berenson, Albert Landsberg, Grete Moll, Hans Purrmann, the heirs of Gertrude and Leo Stein, Captain Edward Steichen, Nelson A. Rockefeller and the Matisse family. Although most items are in English, a reading knowledge of French and German would be beneficial to users.
  - Subgroup I: Matisse Book, 1949-1952
    Includes material Barr used in the creation of his monograph. The four series in this subgroup were organized to reflect the interrelationship between aspects of producing this monograph.
    ca. 1,385 items, not including penciled notes.
    - Subseries A: Correspondence, 1946; 1949-1951
      For preparation of book; ca. 840 items. Correspondence [mostly 1949-51; 6 items 1946; several interesting items 1952]: two filing units of General (A-L, M-Z) followed by 17 units alphabetically arranged by collector or collection.
      - A - L, 1949-1952; Ahlers-Hestermann Art News (Thomas B. Hess) Burlington Magazine(B. Nicholson, Editor) Berès, Pierre Besson, Georges Bignou, Etienne Bradshaw, Mrs. Robert Brummer, Ernest Buchholz Gallery Carstairs Gallery (Georges Keller) Cassirer Ltd., Paul (Grete Ring, Director) Corcoran, Gerald Dimand, Maurice Feigl Gallery Fine Arts Associates (Otto Gerson) Finklestein, Louis (Jewish Theological Seminary) Gold, Alfred Gourgaud Museum Greenberg, Clement Grünewald, Ivan Hamilton, George Heard Highet, Gilbert Hildebrandt, Hans Hope, Henry (Indiana University) Hugo Gallery (Alexander Iolas) Janis, Sidney Kahnweiler, Daniel-Henri (Galerie Louise Leiris) Karpel, Bernard Karpovich, Michael (Harvard University) Kennedy & Co. Kirstein, Lincoln Kleemann Galleries Kraushaar Galleries Lasker, Albert D. Lieberman, William S. London, The Tate Gallery (John Rothenstein) (Box 1, Folder 11.I.A.1)
      - M - Z, 1949-1952; Matisse, Alexina Maugham, Somerset Maurer, Alfred Möll, Greta (Eric Carlson) Morrice, James W. Mosse, Eric P. Matisse Movies Mower, Martin (Fogg Art Museum) Neumann, J.B. (New Art Circle) Norman, Mrs. Edward A. Pach, Walter Palme, Carl Parke-Bernet Galleries Inc. Preface Requin, General Rocaille Chair Rockefeller Center Rogers, Derek Rosenberg, Paul Rosengart, Siegfried Rosenthal, Gertrude (Balto Art Museum) Salz, Sam Seligman, Germain Sloan, Helen F. Smith, Matthew Soby, James Thrall Steinberg, Lionel Earl Stendhal Gallery Steuben Glass Swarzenski, George (Museum of Fine Arts) Terrasse, Charles Thannhauser, Justin Toklas, Alice Vient de Paraître Vietor, Alexander Orr Weber, Max Wheeler, Monroe Whitney Collection (Box 1, Folder 11.I.A.2)
      - Barnes Collection, 1949-1952; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 11.I.A.3)
      - Bell, Clive, 1949-1952; 18 items Letter 6/20/56 included (Box 1, Folder 11.I.A.4)
      - Berenson, Bernard, 1949-1952; 12 items (Box 1, Folder 11.I.A.5)